[Music]
thank you so much sanjie such a pleasure
having you here how have you been
today all good and it's a real pleasure
gorov that we got a Time some to catch
up with you finally you're here it took
me some time to have you on board on
this podcast but uh sanjie I've always
been an admirer of the kind of work that
you do at IC Lombard and apart from that
I've been an admirer for you because the
kind of life that you have lived the
kind of stories that you have to share
the kind of hobbies and the interests
that you have been able to nurture all
these years so let's take a dive into
your life if you can share one of those
few of those traits that you have picked
up from your childhood that you continue
to cherish and leverage today as
well yes interestingly when you take
back in terms of where I got started uh
I must quickly add to where I come from
uh basically my crucial years which are
the you know critical period of your
life when you are far more
impressionable than otherwise got
started in a very small town called UJ
you know which is in NP that's where I
lived for almost 15 years uh Frankly
Speaking uh a very very average but very
satisfying upbringing in a middle class
family uh we had the joy of small things
which were taught for us getting a new
pair of SL papers meant far more than
probably what means to the new
generation in terms of what we give them
uh everything was earned for everything
was desired and then achieved with
certain act so there was lot of uh you
know lot of my basic building blocks
probably come from where I grew up in
which environment we grew up a lot of
credit goes to uh the family that I'm
part of which you can't control you need
your share of luck in life to make that
happen so that's what in nutshell has
been my uh most impressionable years
where I grew if you talk talk about life
lessons in terms of what probably would
I recollect I think one critical thing I
realized you know we were far more
aspirational as we were going up growing
days than probably many others there was
in hunger and that was a critical factor
I must also admit as a matter of fact
that uh I was mocer uh in my academics
at least at that point of time in my you
know days of growing up Obsession was
more driven by Sports and in hset if I
look at it it has played a very critical
role in my existence because Sports is
an activity you know you lose every day
but you're not a loser you kind of keep
building up and that has probably been
lot of life lessons which I came I've me
have a whole episode on what is sports
and which way can it you know build a
person in terms of teamwork in terms of
acceptance of losses and so on and so
forth there has been a very very
critical play so if you ask me uh the
whole background the ecosystem the way
and you know the environment that I grew
up played a big role in making me what I
am today uh in that sense thank you
thank you for this beautiful lesson that
you've already shared with us you said
you lose on daily basis and yet you are
not a loser and I'm sure all those
audience who are listening to us right
now with those one of those strike offs
they t to at least I have labeled myself
as a loser just because I've lost
something it could be a loss of a face
it could be a loss of a contract it
could be
losing and not scoring good marks in a
paper and then I label myself a loser so
you lose on daily basis and yet you're
are not a loser thank you so much sanjie
for bringing that Sanji we all have role
models in our life and since you're
talking about the impressionable
ages we all get influenced in our
lives there are people who have impacted
us beyond our imagination who has
influenced you the most in your life
it's a very interesting question in
terms of who's influenced me the most uh
clearly uh you fall back on parents and
when you fall back on parents it's like
you know asking parent which is your
favorite son it's set T question to
reply and for me it's equally difficult
but in terms of someone who I'm admired
who had in the growing up years in I was
very close I think my mom uh uh amazing
lady in many ways I think she has had
this huge balance that she created in
life uh I'll give you an anecdote
probably I'll fast forward you know in
our growing years when promotions meant
a lot more uh in a life I reached out to
her once when I had a very good
so-called increment and stroke you know
carer growth one has to speak about it
at that moment all I expected was
celebration Jubilation in terms of what
you have done and in that moment that
call and those were those landline call
days right there were no mobiles in the
in those
days you know she came back to say you
know you mean a lot it's good that you
got what you wanted to and I'm sure you
deserved it but we would still love you
as much as we would if you wouldn't have
got all this also so you should just
stay where you are so this middle of the
road approach uh so it's like this you
know they keep talking about it when
things are really going good uh it's
unfair to think it's because of you and
I think are going very bad which happens
in every careers you know in intraday
there's so much of fluctuation for all
of us I mean if you do submissions of
life God knows where all what all we all
must have faced whether me or you gorov
we all have stories to speak about it
she added a sense of calmness sense of
you know by giving upfront feedback in
terms of what's to be appreciated what
not it balanced me a lot more but that
being said I would not take away what my
dad was because his ability to manage
his professional life he was a very
successful you know corporate uh career
person who's done pretty well and Rose
up the ranks in a very difficult Manner
and did well so there was that from
there probably the ability to balance
out whatever little I balance I'm not
the right person to answer if you ask my
wife she'll definitely say no no he's
shot on 50 things but that being put
aside where it is that's the influence
you had in my life yeah yeah and I love
the story that you shared about your
mother
when in the middle of the road she said
I love you as much as I've always and no
accomplishments of yours are going to
take away that love and no challenges in
your life are going to take away either
you know reminds me of my conversation
with my
mother she was making that theim and
this story I've shared on this podcast
so many times she was making D and I
came back home and while she was making
d right the the process of be incurred
is you pour that warm water in that
yeast right and you keep it after you
keep it for some time and during the
entire process she was saying wuru wuru
wuru wuru wuru and I said Mom for this
simple task why are you
bothering
aan and she said so beautiful she she
said it so beautifully G of at no point
in time I want to live in this
impression and that is my way of
expressing my interesting and that's the
reason I carry this value of
shukrana always with me oh wow that
whatever I'm doing it's happening
through me not because of me well said
very well said absolutely absolutely and
that stayed with me and as you are
talking about the values that you have
picked up from your father I think
parents play a very vital role in
helping us become who we are so thank
you for this beautiful reminder Sanji
what were those defining moments in your
life that helped you reach where you
have reached do what you do become who
you have
become I think valid question I think uh
there are a few things which have
happened uh some driven by Destiny some
driven in many ways with choices you
make uh but the big moment was as I said
I have grown up in a small town called
uan and uh how did this movement of uan
to Mumbai happen you know that time used
to be called Bombay clearly my dad
changed his job in uan to Bombay uh like
any other person I was trying to be an
aspiring cricketer in those days and I
was doing extremely well in the city
called ujin and at that point of time I
felt that Mumbai will be a disaster
because I can come up the ranks
eventually over there and and refus to
leave uen and come to Mumbai with my dad
and at that point of time uh my dad also
take took a call that okay you live
there with Mom and probably I'll do the
transit up down andever required over
weekends and so on and so forth but in
two months he realized that he can't do
while he can live without us he can't
live without Mom and so he said that I'm
taking Mom along you take your call
where you want to be I was forced to
move from Udan to Mumbai and there a
couple of things which happened which
became eventually lifelessness so my
obsession was cricket was uh impacting
my academics in a very big way at that
point of time because it's not that I
was bad but that I wasn't interested and
clearly if you're not interested you
eventually start showing it in your
results also in some way or the other he
said that you need to make uh choice in
terms of what you want to be and when we
came to Mumbai uh he took me to multiple
grounds in one of those visits to show
as to what talent is who are the people
who are playing and where do I uh belong
and at that time at that point of time
when I saw I was like a frog in a well
right I had no clue what the outside
world was all about uh I lost my
conviction in terms of whether I can
have a career in cricketing life uh it
was a very significant moment uh and
conviction is everything what you
believe in probably eventually can
happen
because you will be all in and you will
make it work but that conviction went
again I could easily move towards more
academically oriented I would never say
that I would be calling myself a great
student but I was clearly you know
moving in the direction that this what
my chosen life this one event was very
critical uh but I had not much of a role
to play but uh I'm thankful that
eventually Destiny propelled me and my I
could my mind could take the right call
at the right time to make that a reality
the other one is a very interesting one
in terms of what happened after 12th you
know by the time my academics were
sorted I was becoming you know I was
getting my decent position in the class
I I got very good numbers uh when I got
very good Marks in My 12th standards
apparently I was told by my college
which was in chimu swam the principal
wanted me to stay back as one of the few
show call students that you know we've
got good people who can hang in and
probably do what is required uh I was
pretty tough you know I made a very
clear statement why would I stay in a
place like Swami vand you know I'm just
moving on and my college of choice is
arar and that's where I'll go and uh
pursue my bom and post that whatever I
want to get myself educated and uh
interestingly when pod list came in for
admission I was probably among the top
100 students blah blah in Mumbai and
blah all of that thing was there uh my
name was not then the admission list and
I was shocked I said it's obviously a
judgment of error right the were people
way below my marks who have gotten and
if you know that time life was easy you
get your marks and you get admission
there was no other uh attribution being
done uh and my name missing I rushed uh
very very arrogantly to the principal's
cabin where I was not allowed to go in
and at that point of time I told the guy
the The Watchman who was there outside
saying about there's an error and I need
my admission to be
confirmed uh I was not allowed in when
the principal I waited when the
principal walked out I told him sir
there's a judgment error because I have
this marks people well below me even 8
10 person below me have got it what have
I done there please corrected and get me
my admission because I have taken uh the
TC you know from there and I've not
applied anywhere because I thought this
is the only College I wanted to be and
this is the place and that point of time
he said listen I have taken this year
marks of 10th and 12th and on the
average of it that was never been done
in Mumbai ever I said what then I said I
was cbsc can you give me the grace mark
because that time CBS to get extra 5%
10% he said no I've decided no Grace
Mark marks are marks whether whichever
board you are and look my average f down
and I could not get admission uh it was
chaos it was chaos and the uh the little
bit of arrogance with which I said I
will not work in Swami since I had no
other college left to join I was without
admission I was beyond any forms being
field all of the process was over I was
left without an admission at that point
of time gorov I had no choice I went
back to the principal at Swami and I
told him give me an admission I really
don't have an admission and I got
admitted there
and I was living life probably in a
shell as luck would have it my my folks
knew I wasn't comfortable he said let's
apply for sidnam I said why will snum
take me which was typically that time
the best college I applied in a month's
time sidam had some cancellation and
they gave me the
admission now the interesting question
is and which is what I wanted to put
across to you that it's pure Destiny in
terms of where I was supposed to go so I
was not meant for pod I moved to s
and I had to again go and tell that
principle that listen I need to leave
Swami
again which actually was the tougher
part so first time when I declined I was
an arrogant guy who was trying to say
why will I stay I go back to the same
person and I plead that please give me
admission I'm left without an admission
now here I again leaving that place to
go to syam because my choice was how
much of hard it was to travel from chimu
to church gate I want to be in syam but
what I learned was and that is life and
that lesson State you don't need to burn
your Bridges you need to keep lot more
equity in terms of your conduct in terms
of your composure because you don't know
where life will take you it's it's it's
a very very it's a very quirky existence
we have we do give ourselves lot of
importance but that's not where the play
comes in when I went back this time to
the principal I was my humble self I
would remain thankful all his life I
told him it's embarrassing but that's
the reality but I want to move on and
the magnanimity of that person rather
than mine was that he very gracefully
accepted that yes you should move on
there because that is the best college
and so on and so forth so the message
got landed and my lesson was that life
will take you wherever you want to but
you need to make sure that you let it
flow in a manner which your conduct is
not out of s so that was another and I
think syum was
uh very very defining moment and that is
where I say to everybody that the
environment that you choose choose at
times can make you better than what you
are and syum was full on exposure it was
uh a townside college there were a lot
of people with lot of wealth as well as
lot of intelligence you need to pick
your people but it was truly truly
transformational so I
mean couple of things in terms of uh
what I'm able to narrate
about uh what had an impact and what
changed me yeah thank you thank you for
such a beautiful narration of what
happened and as I'm just reflecting you
said that's a question that I have for
you
gorov I would say there's no question
for me uh Sanji from where I look at
life when people ask me G how have you
been able to reach where you have
reached what are those defining moments
I personally believe if there are two
pillars which have supported me reach
where I've reached help me become who
I've become I would say the first one is
Grace people call it luck people call it
Destiny I call it Grace it's sheer luck
it's sheer my good fortune that I'm born
the family that I'm born into I'm
friends with the people that I'm friends
with the education that I got the people
that I worked with and on day-to-day
basis the kind of people that I get to
speak to for example this opportunity to
interact with you sanjie is I think it's
if it's not Destiny I don't know what to
call this that's
one second thing I believe is what has
worked for me in my life is genuine
connections I mean I personally believe
that once I make good connection with
someone I make
sure that I should be of
some service to the other person and
when I'm saying service is the question
that I ask myself is how can I be an
eased to work with how can I leave the
other person with a little bit of
hope that he did not enter the
conversation with and as I was listening
to your listening to you I was
reflecting and you have already
acknowledge
the magnanimity of the
principle in the first go when he
requested you and when you denied he
accepted that when you reached out to
him again he accepted that third time
when you reached out to him he accepted
that yep and here I'm wondering what a
beautiful human being he would have been
yeah absolutely where he's willing to
accept the so-called arrogance the
so-called surrender the so-called the
growth three different phases you showed
up and he was willing to accept you
absolutely fully and completely what a
beautiful magnanimity and the beauty of
these instances is you know what gorov
is something which I remember he
wouldn't even recollect it right because
he's dealing with thousands of students
it's a huge institution but this is what
influence is all about what stays with
you it's very personal and it just just
stays that's the way it works yeah you
know you said something so beautiful you
said that we should not be taking
ourselves to see seriously you use the
word that we should not give ourselves
more importance that's what you
mentioned also I remember sanj in our
last conversation you mentioned that at
times most of us all of us tend to
undersell ourselves so my question is
what do you think where does that come
from and what can be done
instead I think uh very well said g and
I I see this part of it uh so I'm aware
of the fact that I being in a job which
is primarily driven by numbers sales and
so on and so forth uh this communication
of push and pull on targets and so on
and so forth is a part of my existence
uh but the acknowledgement of it came to
an instance uh which is why I'll reflect
and tell you yes there is a challenge
I'm rehabbing with a particular injury
that I have at this point of time and I
got a new coach for myself uh uh his
name is vul and is a very interesting
person who himself is a chart accountant
uh but he's following his passion of
being a physical trainer rather than
following a profession like me who are
who's working a more conventional man in
a company and doing a uh job clearly so
when he used to ask me I used to put
weights and you say how was the weight
my answer used to be in English which
said that it is okay you know it is fine
maybe maybe not and he said why are you
underselling yourself that's where he
started telling and I should get very
annoyed for first few occasions I really
pushed him back saying why do you say
under selling and all because it's not
fair and that's what AG does to you
right you harden your own existence your
own belief and you think that you're not
understanding he said I'm just giving
you a reply for a question he said no on
a scale of 10 you need to start telling
me whether it was 6 8 nine wherever you
felt nine means it was really tough six
means it was relatively easy I want
finite answers because I can see the mov
I have enough observation power to know
that you were very comfortable but you
want to not take the next level and I
when he gave me this whole description
for you know 10 15 minutes in terms of
how I'm
reacting and he was like a you know
principal who trying to say I don't want
you to understand if the weight is light
you say increase yourself rather than I
insisted because when I'm insisting you
feel I'm pushing it on you while you
could actually from your own mind accept
it so if you see our own existence of
what we do in working life we have a
tendency to say that if I'm going to do
X I'll say no no x - 20% is what I can
achieve because because if I achieve X
plus 5 x - 10 above 5% on that I'm
better off so this to me got stuck and I
realized that a lot of times in life we
have a tendency to underplay because you
don't want to put your neck up uh
clearly I can narrate one small incident
to make my point you know I was doing a
lot of half marathons at early part of
my running days and people started
saying in next 6 to 12 months what next
why don't you do a full Marathon I
wasn't willing to commit I said no I
will see in my mind I was clearly you
know calculating my heart wanted to do
full Marathon right naturally but then I
made a self declaration that if I do my
half marathon under two hours then I'll
probably try for full otherwise I won't
it continued for two years uh nor could
I give a shot nor could I do my half
Bild between two months and then finally
I said let me register for full my first
reaction for registering for full
was
so this is another classic case of
underselling it but Frankly Speaking
it's a stupid thing to do eventually I
realize that by declaring your plans of
what you want to be you make yourself
physically and mentally far more
acceptable you you align your ecosystem
aligns your own mind with your heart
aligns and then you can achieve it
eventually in a rough conversation with
someone in a party I said of course I'm
also doing full I didn't tell you and
I felt liberated I thought I've taken a
weight out of my chest in terms of
disclosing it this is what I want to do
and the next half which was a
preparation to full I did under two
probably after that I've done so many of
them under two so what probably when I
say this under selling
business decided that I want to put
across my plans to as many as possible
because it's only fair and there's no
shame in not achieving what You' spoken
about but the fact is that alignment is
complete so this probably is one of the
critical things which I wanted to share
yeah thank you so much and since then
you have done so many full marathons as
well not only in India but globally as
per my understanding you have completed
15 full marathons including Boston
Marathon as well is my understanding
right uh yeah I have done that I have
done that yes you're right you're right
AB what started as a hobby has become
part so help me understand let's let's
double click on that why is it important
for people who are working in the
corporate world or people who have run
their own businesses people who are
entrepreneurs and on startups right why
is it important for all of us to have
hobbies and interest apart from outside
our work I think a very very fair
question and gorov I can you know
probably tell you uh anybody of anybody
each one of us existing in whichever
life uh cannot be 24 by seven thinking
of same things all the time I firmly
believe that any point of time each one
of us will have in multiple sections
success and failure it can be in your
personal life where you are actually
going through the worst times while
typically your corporate times you're
going through your highest you know in
my early days in my college when I was
working with the computer company as a
sales promoter for them I remember a
person was given a ticket uh to go to
USA you know and it was a big thing in
the '90s to go to USA for a for an
exceptional performance and the same
time after one hour he got a warning
letter in terms of low performance I
said how does this work in life how can
you have a ticket to us he said this was
for the sale that I did three months
back and post that my numbers have
dropped so this is for the recency on so
your success reward was coming with a
lag while the failure of last three
months came immediately on its table in
terms of things a warning and to me as a
student see I was look still living my
college life it was a big perplexing
situation that how can an organization
give both of them on the same day it was
pure coincidence but that is the way you
know things come out so coming back to
uh my running piece in terms of what uh
you know got me into it uh is pure
random luck because the environment
changed marathons became a big thing and
I got sucked into it uh from there
on uh it actually became an idty believe
me when I had to skip one or two
introductions even for my working life
used to be saying the way you said
someone's running marathon uh look I had
a dream and I told about that at the
start that I wanted to be known more as
a sports person than a working life
person right so there was a clear
element of it in heart and not in my
mind I started enjoying it I I thought
I'm getting acknowledged uh for what I
was typically born with uh and uh in
terms of my own passion uh clearly also
connected to this is
I love bucketing in my life you know I
don't want it all combined in submission
so I don't want spillovers of my working
life into personal personal into sports
and the moment you keep bucketing them
and live it in isolation so that many
times I've said that the best part of my
life is probably you know 5:30 in the
morning when I go for my running or my
tennis and I'm finishing it by probably
7:00 and from there on I'm rolling in
waiting for the next morning to come in
but waiting for the next morning you end
up giving a lot more because you know
there's something exciting waiting and
it's not about running it's not about
tennis it's about what you like if you
like
singing start getting into that there's
so many people you'll meet who will say
I used to sing but I stopped singing so
many will say I used to dance but I
stopped dancing I mean my own brother
right he was a very good player better
player than me but he stopped all of
that in terms of doing it if you are not
able to pursue this current life has
become a lot more stressful bucketing is
the way forward G and as much uh you
know so there are spillovers let's be
honest we all are human but you are able
to pick up the good parts you know you
get in trouble with friends but you have
something else which is comeing your way
so you you pick up the good part let the
bed once Passover and we know that you
know this Shall Pass recuperating from
the in injuries that you get getting
back all of it becomes part of a mix and
you end up living a relatively more
healthier existence than what will
happen if you have not bucketed your
life is what I
feel this is so beautiful you know
yesterday only I was talking to a very
senior seite
executive he happens to Works in he
happens to work in an technology company
and he was talking about something
called portfolio
life and what you talking about the
bucketed it's absolutely on the same
lines that you know why it's really
important to have a portfolio of work
that you're involved in abolutely um
sanjie you also spoke about identity and
that's something that I would like to
double click on as we move on but before
that I remember during our last
conversation you mentioned a beautiful
term you said victims of their own
intelligence where you mention that at
times we become our own biggest
enemies tell me more about that when
you're using the term victims of their
own intelligence how does that impact
first what is that and how does that
impact an organization and the people
working with you so you know I give an
interesting anecdote uh to make my point
so I have multiple examples on that but
one you know so there was a person who
came for his internship from IM am Amad
and worked with us and you know I was
part of the interview team and I
selected him I really like the guy in
terms of what he could bring to the
table and I found him extremely sharp
well aware of you know what can do so in
the internship uh he had a great time
and he said I want my final placement uh
with you guys itself and I would come
and join your department clearly I was
very enthused and I said wow uh
internship you know is only a couple of
months ofair but if you were able to
pick it up we were more than happy to
give him a pre-placement offer uh and
quite rightly so he came and join in uh
very interestingly his sharpness when he
started working with us naturally there
was a lot of attention also being given
because of the cege as well as the
ability to make a difference in the
department you know our play is all
about having good people making good
things work a month from now he came
very harassed and he said I need a
personal time and guidance from you I
said why not fair enough let's have a
discussion he was very perturbed he said
that listen I mean where is my career
going I don't know what I'm doing I'm
not sure I said what's troubling you you
just about work for a month or more and
there's nothing to be concerned you
already spent some time uh you're on
track but said listen there is there is
some Gap in terms of where it is he
wasn't opening up I said okay let's do
one thing give yourself a month from now
or maybe couple of weeks and then we
meet again because you seemed a lot more
troubled when he came again uh in a
couple of months
time he made a very interesting play he
said see my friends are someone's in
foreign Bank someone's G here for
training and here I'm doing this stuff
I'm not convinced that my career is
going the right direction so I had a
very interesting take on him he was a
person who knew too much too soon
probably uh was evaluating his career on
daily basis see you live daily but you
live your finally it's in sumission in
Co HS that you look at it I mean when I
speaking about it you know I talk about
my life in my life in Mumbai and then
probably you know how I moved to s so
you talk you look back but you don't
assess it so I said you need to be
patient and if you're looking back and
seeing what others are doing Frankly
Speaking there will be some probably
working in the investment banking of New
York in the best of the best investment
Banks some will be doing this it's your
personal call of what works with you uh
I have realized that too much of
intelligence at times can be innovating
Factor you need to carry it lightly you
need to your ability to relate to people
at large can get compromised I've got
another few examples in terms of saying
so it is an asset which needs to be
really cherished invested in so that you
maintain that I'm not even for a second
saying that please don't use it but to
make that as a top of your recall in
terms of what's required making yourself
Brash and your inability to consume
average see listen I mean if you are
part of a 2% top CER 1% for that matter
you are a blessed soul but the bulk of
it would be still lying in those you
there a normal distribution that comes
into play will ly in the 90% coher and
that is what you need to relate to that
is what you need to work on a classical
example I always keep saying is you know
uh you you got to invest yourself to be
I mean tendulka did not become tendulka
because he was talented he was still
putting in 10 hours of work eics every
day I mean CI and T were both on similar
track one was more talented I think C
was more talented but you had a tendar
who probably made a name and fame for
himself eventually right so there is
there is a play that is required you are
natural with some things you should
harness it but I have seen multiple
times uh this becomes a restrictive
factor and that in any team exercise in
that in terms of gr personally can
become restrictive so value it but don't
get obsessed with it and don't throw it
around because the World At Large
doesn't care yeah yeah yeah you know
there's a beautiful book that I read
long time back it says Talent is
overrated yeah and as I'm just listening
to you another word which is talking to
me is
consistency and then as you mentioned
that you cannot continue to re-evaluate
how well are you progressing on
day-to-day basis you live on daily basis
you know Steve Jobs said it you cannot
connect the dots looking forward you can
only connect them looking backwards so
I'm sure uh he had some reason why he
said what he said sanj let's shift the
gears one of my deep interests is to
understand the
challenges people experience on
day-to-day basis especially leaders at
se Suite
level so my question to you is what are
the top three
challenges that you face in your
day-to-day life and how do you ensure
that you stay relevant and deal with
them well a very very fair point clearly
the generation that we belong to with
the 50s we grew without mobile we grew
without social media we uh I'm just
coming out of a presentation where they
said that almost 45% of the ads spent
now on the digital side uh it's it's
been a transformational existence I
think we've seen the transitions you
know many ways we've been you
know fortunate to see the transition uh
I mean we all can't recollect how we
used to land at an airport and call our
driver we we've got this so much of
confusion you I lost my mobile in Delhi
and I didn't know how do I come back to
Mumbai and we connect and do what is
required and which we doing it in a very
very clear you get used to the good
things and they are like drugs you get
addicted to it uh being relevant is one
of the topmost things you know that uh
hits my mind in terms of the top of the
chart recall clearly G and I have seen
over time you need to work hard and look
at any profession for that matter if you
meet a doctor he'll say that for the
rest of his life he keeps reading
because medicine keeps changing right
there is there is no way what he was
taught and what is relevant and the top
most doctors are the ones who are right
now probably in their 60s and 70s you
know doing the most
delicate and intricate you know
procedures and you know curing they
they've got the hand of God uh in many
ways to heal people so my my point is
that that's what's true for even
professionals like us people who are in
working life uh the investment to self
so we work for a brand like I'm I'm
blessed to be supported by a brand Which
is far bigger than people like me and
can survive without people like me so my
own belief is in a c existence which
you're talking about if at all there is
a term like this uh I have my own views
on these things but but that being said
uh we need to make sure that we draw
benefit of of it and I believe that uh
clearly this brand has invested a lot
more in me to make me look good than
what I could have contributed to make it
look better right so we're doing our
bits and pieces but clearly we are
blessed to have it you know if you take
the brand away from where I work uh I
don't even know how many LinkedIn
followers I will have I don't know how
many friends I'll have there is there's
of course some bit of a belief there
certain certain crosssection of people
probably be there but that's again my
presumption still to be tested uh with
time I I do believe there will be a
substantial fall on all of this so
substance over form has to be understood
and if that is what is required you keep
investing it because that's what has
given you a life if you and me are
talking we are talking because I'm doing
something and I ran into you it's the
brand that got me connected to it's not
sanjie monri per which got connected so
that confusion at times of conflicting
ourselves with the brand is one thing
which is avoidable uh because it is
transitionary everything uh does have a
time frame and
clearly in that light that kind of
existence becomes a very important piece
and also one more thing which is there
uh which I like is that you ability to
relate I think team plays a significant
role so I've learned in any sports game
right in terms of where what it is some
will get acknowledged a lot more I mean
a striker gets acknowledged a lot more
than a
Defender it's it's part of the process
so your ability to understand which part
of the role you are in and conquering it
so favorite saying you know when I meet
a panala who's becoming famous right you
go to a much p in Mumbai and everybody
wants to go there and eat that
P
right and that is what you you don't go
and ask it's irrelevant right it is like
an obsessive so even if I meet a player
who's played at a state level or even at
a district level for that matter I'm
obsessively looking at him for that
piece of art so our same thing as
so-called leadership job that we are
doing our ability to dive very
obsessively in that to make it work
becomes a very critical aspect because
we need to pick up the skills you know
as a kid I used to do all those events
in my Colony that I used to live in
Frankly Speaking I wasn't good with
anything but still I was driving team
because I had so many smart people who
were willing to come along and jel
together to make that work if
contribution minimalistic but I knew
that with if to get them together and
make it work will probably be the best
contribution I can do so it's it's those
pieces of normalization which becomes
very critical for
survival so first thing that I'm
listening is staying relevant how do you
ensure that you continue to learn and
that's the reason why doctors and
lawyers they are known as practicing
doctor practicing lawyer practicing
chartered accountant okay and the second
thing that you mentioned about is
managing your team members rallying
people together so that the normalized
results would be more than what
individually you can drive is my
understanding right absolutely
absolutely you said absolutely spot on
so that's the way it is yeah yeah okay
thank you sanjie
sanjie all my conversations with you
have left me with profound
Reflections in fact you one of those
very few people that I've come across
who have
challenged the acceptable Norms of
leadership and I'll tell you why in all
my interactions with senior leaders in
the CATE scenario people talk about
leaving
Legacy I remember a few years back I
heard Oprah talking about that I don't
want to leave a legacy I don't believe
in the concept of legacy and during one
of our
conversation you accentuated on the same
lines where you spoke about that you
don't believe in leaving a legacy in
fact in your words you mentioned I'm not
impressed with the word legacy what's
behind that and what could be another
perspective that I might be missing out
on uh no I'm sure I I don't think you're
missing out anything you know I have a
much broader view it's not that we have
not grown up uh uh finding people who
have left Legacy and tremendous respect
for what they've done they've seen
leaders right behind on the screen I can
see Obama Mahatma Gandhi King Martin
Luther you know there is so much that is
clearly there so I have no one to be uh
you know saying that it's not relevant
from a leadership perspective but that
being said I have my own take and I
probably give you an explanation to make
my belief in terms of what I'm trying to
communicate and I use an article you
know which Rahul draid had return
probably in the 90s when he was still
playing for India that he had a chance
to go to a you know under 19 camp in
Bangalore the academy which was there at
that point of time also uh so he saw the
19 people playing uh uh you know and
practicing over there he felt that each
of the players there was a bunch 30
players getting trained over there were
far better than what he was in that
particular age you know they were like
completely you know rock stars and he
said that was each of them can become a
Rahul draid or maybe even Way Beyond
from the talent that they possess so but
in that article also he went on to write
and that's where my take came that out
of these 30 people all who are
practicing and who got to interact with
him probably one or two will play for
the country or maybe even not that
another 57 will play for the state level
another few will play for the district
and so on and so forth so they will do
what is required but they will all move
out of the uh life but will you call the
guy who played only for the country
successful or the other 28 29 some will
run successful businesses some will have
successful corporate life all of that
will come into play what does success
mean right you know so it's easy to make
your own judgment and get obsessed with
it in terms of saying the guy who played
for country are the rock stars because
they will be known they will be
acknowledged and some will play one some
will play 100 test match you can you can
still Google out there's so many of them
who have played less than 10 games for
the country and they've never played but
they played for the country are they all
unsuccessful my one thing is that yes
you need to convert your your habits
your strengths into art like a panal
example right he converted he was making
pan wasn't good one day but he kept
investing you keep hearing stories of
Auto drivers who keep newspapers keep
music systems they keep they attract
customers so what they've done is they
have become so driven that they've gone
on to excel I think that's a relevant
piece uh circumstances can make you live
Legacy circumstances can even make you
not leave Legacy right there is a role
that comes in but you go all in and you
do what is required not obsessively
driven and this obsession with Legacy at
times and I was part of lending to
entrepreneurs uh and I was probably
doing lending to entrepreneurs the best
time India has gone through as a phase
you know India shining phase of 20023 to
2007 before the global financial crisis
happened this Obsession to get
acknowledged obsessions to make this can
at times take you over the top and you
may and look it may work it may not work
for all right I cannot leave lead
anybody's life in Marathon has taught me
this right if I my body is able to run a
distance of marathon and life not being
a Sprint but a marathon uh it's hard to
copy others it's hard to get driven to
say B if you can do a full marathon in
three and a half hours probably sanie
can I may have injuries the process
rather than the outcome the journey
rather than the destination can be far
more defining and that is where it's
important and it's not for me to judge
whether it's Legacy or what it is what
it is thank you thank you so much for
bringing that aspect in
fact the natural progression and the
next question for me is going to Loop in
when you use the word identity and then
you use the um sentence where you said
that at times we tend to take ourselves
more important you also spoke about that
the brand that we represent is much
bigger than who we are on the contrary
in today's corporate world sanjie you
will find that people tend to take them
themselves too seriously and more
important than they actually are and
because of which what happens is when
they take themselves too seriously they
distend
themselves from the
reality what's happening at the
grassroot level at the ground level how
do you ensure that you stay
grounded both literally and
metaphorically because in all my
conversations with you I've never
smelled an arrogance any kind of air I
think you being kind and frankly
speaking this is one part is hard for me
to judge personally
and if you're saying it I would uh
accept it with all humbleness but uh
it's a lot to do with upbringing uh
probably life has been a lb you know in
terms of many things uh and I can tell
you all of us and it's a big one which I
believe in uh we have been very lucky
because life has given not even Second
Chance third chance fourth chance and
then we've been able to make it look at
the admission piece which I spoke about
it right not getting into poda getting
into back to Swami and then probably to
sidnam clearly it was all about getting
multiple chances so there was an there
was a moving mass of
course the decision had to be taken and
somewhere I said let's go and be in syam
I was was I daunted initially uh the
reality of life is yes I was daunted
that to be in a townside college
where uh you know you you've heard
stories about what all it leads to uh
but but I realized whichever environment
you go in you do find and you do manage
to get like-minded people and you can
probably you know live through it in
whichever way it is I remember meeting
my friends in s and I was trying to over
bely prove to them that I belong to
where truly actually I didn't belong and
I went out for a lunch with them from
college and I realized that what they
spend over a lunch or something which I
probably spend over next two to three
months you had to retract so there are
and it was not about the fact that I
couldn't afford it that was not the that
was the least of my worry it's about how
do I get people who are like me and you
find it and they're equally there and
your time can come if you hang in so
there is there is that play that comes
in and it's a lot to do with the
ecosystem which you are part of which
keeps you where you belong and sports I
think has made me realize that you
cannot win every game shot that you hit
will not go where it's supposed to be
and there will be days when you will hit
everything which will go and touch the
line and there will be days when you
will not so as a person I'm not the one
who can believe it but good days if you
can make it count more than the bad days
you will probably get sorted eventually
beautiful what a beautiful learning you
know as I'm just listening to you I'm
going back to the statement that you
made that I might lose on day one and
day two and yet I'm not a loser
similarly I might win today and tomorrow
and yet I'm not a winner I am because I
exist and that itself is a blessing the
question is am I willing to count the
blessings more than the days where I'm
not very happy sanj just take me one
step
forward the background that you come
from I'm sure you would have some
myths that would have broken once you
started to walk this path right now a
senior executive with one of the biggest
organization in the country today having
walked this path what do you think what
are the myths that people tend to carry
and are absolutely not true at your
level I think uh in a way I've covered
that but I'll probably reiterate that
circumstances can make you look much
better than what you are and the other
way also can come out true where it can
look make you look much worse than what
you are so Frankly Speaking uh it's
important to look at every existence in
you know in a contextual Manner and let
it roll I do believe in living the
moment I do believe in enjoying what has
come by me there's no way I would say
that I'm the I'm not the monk who sold
this Ferrari actually I wouldn't mind
one so all of that
is uh pretty much intact but uh you have
to look in context I mean I I I don't
know how successful or you know how out
of sorts I have been in my own existence
but clearly
I do believe that and again it's a lot
to do with how you have come up in life
I'm able to see the the good part of my
existence in terms of how blessed uh
life that we've had and to that extent
you stay where it is but uh it's you
need to know that you need to let it
pass and you know have a very good
belief that uh everyone gets a golden
lap in
life and that golden lap most most of us
don't even realize that we are going
through a golden lab and it does it does
pass out right in the end it's not a
perpetuity of so that acknowledgement of
the golden lap uh which you're running
through where everything what you touch
eventually becomes gold and and when
that run gets over you feel that
everything is becoming mud uh it's it's
something which is you need to adjust to
and you live with it's like a aging body
right what I could do in 20s as a sports
person not able to do in my 50s so uh
but I haven't taken away the enjoyment
that comes out of that uh probably I
could play seven days a week but now I
play three days a week but since it is
becoming less I've started enjoying more
it was very high but it wasn't there so
there is a very very clear
acknowledgement of
existence thank you so much thank you so
much sanjie for an
absolute insightful conversation just
the last
question having lived the life that you
have
lived
what do you know for sure with 100%
certainty good one I think uh clearly go
of so I'm 100% certain that in the long
run we all are
dead there is no confusion there is a
finality to our existence and that has
to be acknowledged and accepted uh so
clearly you must do what you believe in
and I have spoken about multiple
instances of how obsessively
I'm involved uh with our my own
existence uh clearly if you ask me I
also believe that when I say the word
obsessive I want to use it in a very
moderate manner to say that I do believe
we need to take care of ourselves if we
need take care of others there is there
is a process uh that is involved in that
and
uh on 100% certainty that reality is
there having been having having taken a
birth and a life to leave lead that
which is there at this point of time
there would be a finality and in that
intervening
period try to do what you can yeah thank
you so much yeah that is that's for sure
that one day we all are going to live
this world and what we do today is what
we would have so thank you so much Sanji
for for your time for your wisdom for
sharing your experiences and all the
lovely stories that you have to share
thank you so much and you have a
wonderful day ahead take care absolute
pleasure connecting with you gorov and
uh clearly you've taken me back in time
and that's always a pleasure so thank
you so much for this endearing
discussion thank you so
[Music]
much